NYSUT Vice President's office files. 6174/002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- PERFORMANCE: (Box 20)
  - Closing the Performance Gap Committee 2000-2002 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    Cortese talking points for April 30 meeting of Closing the Performance Gap Committee; press release from State Education Department, "Vast Majority of High School Seniors Pass Regents English, Math Exams to Graduate," with attached statistical charts, December 19, 2001; agenda for meeting of Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction; draft document by Regents and Statewide Performance Advisory Council, "Strategies to Close the Gaps in Student Performance," with similar cover letters to Cortese from Commissioner Mills, October 22, 2001, and January 9, 2002; report by Comptroller H. Carl McCall, "Higher Standards for All: New York State's Educational Performance Gap and Necessary Reforms," July 2000; related student achievement data; handwritten notes
  - Statewide Gap Implementation Advisory Committee 2/12/02, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 22)
    State Education Department briefing paper on No Child Left Behind Act; discussion paper for Regents on uses of disaggregated data in closing the performance gap (reporting performance data by racial, ethnic, and other demographic characteristics); list of members of Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction; statistical materials
  - Performance Gap Meeting. Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction 9/26/02, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 23)
    Summary of issues discussed at meetings of Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction; report by subcommittee: "Closing the Gaps in Student Academic Performance"
  - Statewide Performance Gap 7/1/02, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 24)
    Agenda for Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction meeting; Regents report, "Strategies to Close the Gaps in Student Performance," February 2002; comparison of Regents report and report of Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction; Regents status report of middle-level education in NYS; issue outline, "Improving Middle-Level Instruction"; final report of the NYSUT Task Force on Time, June 2002
  - Performance Gap Advisory Committee 4/30/02, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    Agenda for Subcommittee on Strengthening Instruction meeting; Cortese talking points; Regents discussion paper re implementation of learning standards for science, technology, health, physical education, and family and consumer sciences in NYS public schools, year III district level study, February 25, 2002; handwritten notes
  - Performance Gap Advisory Committee 3/14/02, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    Promotional brochures for the University of the State of New York; agendas for subcommittees
- Performance Learning Systems. See: Project T.E.A.C.H.
- Pay for Performance 1997-2000 (Box 20, Folder 27)
  Consortium for Policy Research in Education (CPRE) Policy Brief: "The Motivational Effects of School-Based Performance Awards, February 2000; CPRE State-Level Knowledge and Skill-Based Pay Survey summary of results, with cover letter to NYSUT (as survey respondent), December 27, 1999; Douglas County Federation of Teachers Performance Pay Plan for Teachers; 1997-2000 Agreement between Kenmore-Town of Tonawanda Union Free School District and the Kenmore Teachers Association covering Full and Part-time Teachers; Newark Teachers' Association letter to Cortese re performance pay option, May 20, 1997
- Policy. See: NYSUT Policy Council; see: AFT Program and Policy Council
- NYSUT Public Policy Seminar 7/22/99. 3/28/00, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 28)
  AFT memo re overview of policies linked to gains in student achievement, 7/22/99; seminar presentation outline, "Money Matters in Education. When Spent on What Works," March 28, 2000; opening remarks by Cortese; letter inviting Commissioner Mills to public policy seminar
- Pouring Rights 2001 (Box 20, Folder 29)
  Questions and answers re legal issues re State Education Department policy re "pouring rights" contracts (contracts between school districts and soft drink vending machine companies, often requiring long-term installation of vending machines in return for up-front fees to districts)
- Pre-Kindergarten Program 2000 (Box 20, Folder 30)
  Comparison of experimental and universal pre-K; AFT early childhood education survey for locals, with cover letter February 11, 2002; State Education Department Directory of NYS Funded Prekindergarten Programs, November 2000; memo to Cortese re NYS Universal Prekindergarten Program, January 5, 2001; excerpts from Commissioner's Regulations re universal and experimental pre-K programs; list of school districts participating in the Universal Prekindergarten Program for 2000-01 school year; draft NYSUT policy on universal prekindergarten; correspondence. See also: Early Childhood Education (Pre-School), Albert Shanker Institute
- Pre-K, Universal. Class Size 12/17/97, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 31)
  Meeting notice; text of legislation; notice to school districts by State Education Department of agreement on legislation
- Pre-K, Universal 11/7/97, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  Memo to NYSUT officers summarizing new law, September 24, 1997; letter to Cortese from State Education Department announcing law establishing universal pre-K program, inviting her to join work group, October 9, 1997; draft outline of NYSUT policy issues, 10/16/97; NYSUT Universal Prekindergarten Information Sheet, 1997; memo, preliminary analysis of universal pre-K regulations, with attached regulations, and summary of regional SED meeting, October 24, 1997; related materials and correspondence
- Pre-K Compromise (Not) 1988-1997 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  Cover message re failure to find evidence of attempt at compromise on pre-K programs, noting contents of folder, 1997; letter (draft) to Gov. Cuomo from Cortese arguing that day care cannot be provided outside a school setting, November 15, 1988; letter from NYSUT director Charles Santelli to Council on Children and Families, asserting that day care field is fragmented, that provision of early childhood education should be restricted to public schools, October 19, 1988; policy paper by NYS Child Care Coordinating Council, "Early Childhood Education: A Collaborative Approach," 1989; Report of Proceedings of Legislative Symposium on Early Childhood Programs, February 3-4, 1988
- Pre-Kindergarten. Report by Lt. Gov. Betsy McCaughey Ross 1996 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  Report #1, Prep. For Success: Expanding Pre-K & Educational Day Care, September 1996; NYSUT press release praising report, September 4; memos to Cortese critiquing report
- Task Force to Study the Preparation and Licensure of School Administrators and Supervisors 1989 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  Report of the task force to Commissioner of Education Thomas Sobol, March 27, 1989; letter from Sobol to NYSUT vp Cortese, thanking her for her work on the task force. See also: Standards & Assessment
- Task Force to Study the Preparation and Licensure of School Administrators and Supervisors February 8, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  Task force meeting materials, including agenda, draft report to Commissioner, suggested revisions of report by Collegiate Association for the Development of Educational Administration; comments by other school organizations
- Task Force to Study the Preparation and Licensure of School Administrators and Supervisors October 1988 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  Position Paper on Licensing and Certification, by Council of Supervisors and Administrators of the City of New York; related position papers; meeting notice; September 20 and October 5 minutes; list of task force members; handwritten notes
- Task Force to Study the Preparation and Licensure of School Administrators and Supervisors November 7, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  Task force meeting agenda; November 7 minutes; press release from New Jersey Department of Education, "State Board Set for Final Consideration of Principal Licensing Plan," July 20, 1988; related materials from New Jersey; printed publications: "The New York Report: A Blueprint For Learning and Teaching: Report of the Commissioner's Task Force on the Teaching Profession," March 1988; "A Blueprint for the Professionalization of Teaching," by NYS School Boards Association, NYS Rural Schools Program, NYS Conference of Large City Boards of Education, September 21, 1988; "A View from the Inside: Needs of Beginning Principals," by Leadership in Educational Administration Development Center, School of Education, University at Albany (SUNY), September 1988
- Privatization Project 1992-1996 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  NYSUT Information Bulletin, "The Privatization of Public Schools: Subcontracting Service: nonteaching, teaching, and management," revised February 1995; items for Inside AFT re privatization, February 12, 1996; report by Privatization Task Force, "Privatization Update: A Report to the American Federation of Teachers Executive Council and the K-12 and PSRP Program and Policy Councils," n.d., c. 1995; "Recent Facts and Figures on Private Schools," prepared by the AFT based on the U.S. Department of Education's Private Schools in the United States: A Statistical Profile, 1990-91, January 1995; AFT memo re EAI (Education Alternatives, Inc.) track record, February 17, 1995; article in Education Leadership, "Education for Profit: A Yellow Brick Road to Nowhere," September 1994; Q&A document by Carnegie Council/DRT International Privatization Project, "Privatization: Opportunities for New York," with cover note to Cortese, 1992. See also: Edison; See also: Education Alternatives, Inc.
- PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT:
  See also: Regents Task Force on Teaching; See also: Teacher Education
  - AFT Task Force on Union-Sponsored Professional Development February 2001 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    Working paper not for distribution, "Professional Development for Standards-Based Instruction, October 5, 2000; professional development discussion paper (follow-up to May 28, 2000, meeting sponsored by the Albert Shanker Institute); Albert Shanker Institute publication, "Finding Their Voices: Professionals and Workplace Representation," 2000; report of AFT Task Force on Union- Sponsored Professional Development, June 2001; agenda and materials for February 22-23, 2001, meeting of AFT Task Force on Union-Sponsored Professional Development (including summary report of December 5-6 meeting); memo to Antonia Cortese from Roslyn Brown noting report was not distributed because it "went in a different direction than what AFT was looking for," April 9, 2001; handwritten notes
  - AFT Task Force on Union-Sponsored Professional Development December 2000 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    Brochures, meeting agendas and summaries; reports, handwritten notes
  - AFT Task Force on Union-Sponsored Professional Development October 3-4, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - AFT Professional Development, Albert Shanker Institute 5/31/00, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    Reports and memos
  - AFT Online Professional Development Meeting 1/20/04 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    Teachscape, Your Professional Development Online
  - Professional Staff Congress (PSC) 2000 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    Memo to NYSUT officers re meeting on November 27
- Project T.E.A.C.H. 1977-1984 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  "An Integrated Composite of Successful Teaching Practices," by Performance Learning Systems, Inc., 1977; statistical evaluations of program effectiveness; newsletter; correspondence
- Project T.E.A.C.H.. Meeting with Sandra Feldman 10/12/82, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  Cost estimates for training NYC instructors, 1979-1982; notes about funding and staffing in other states; NYSUT draft agreement with Performance Learning Systems, Inc., c. 1978; description of program and relationship to NYSUT
- Project T.E.A.C.H.. Meeting with Charles Santelli and Tom Willette 6/1/82, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  Letter to Tom Willette, NYSUT, from Joe Hasenstab, Project T.E.A.C.H., re problems with NYC director, May 21, 1982
- Promising Programs 1996-1997 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  "Ten Promising Programs for Educating Disadvantaged Students: Evidence of Impact," Rebecca Harman and Sam Stringfield, Johns Hopkins University, n.d., c. 1994; draft paper, "The Three-Year Effects of 10 Promising Programs on the Academic Achievement of Students Placed at Risk," Sam Stringfield et al., presented to the American Educational Research Association, April 8, 1996; NYSUT Special Order of Business: Reading for Life, 1997; NYSUT memo, HSTW (High Schools That Work) Curriculum for Career-Bound Students, September 2, 1997. See also: AFT Program and Policy Council, K-12 Teachers Meeting
- Proposition 209 (California) 1997 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  Proposed NYSUT policy opposing Proposition 209 banning affirmative action programs
- Quotas, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 20)
  NYSUT brochure, "What Price Quotas?" opposing affirmative action, particularly as implemented by the National Education Association; article on quality circles as union-busting tool. See also: Multicultural Education
- Reading. AFT Task Force on Reading 12/2/98, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  Teachers' Guides for K-2 from Texas Education Inventory; National Education Goals Panel report, "Exploring Rapid Achievement Gains in North Carolina and Texas," November 1998; resolutions adopted at AFT convention, "Beginning Reading Instruction" and "Early Intervention for Students with Behavioral Problems," July 19, 1998; summary of the Reading Excellence Act; full text of legislation; agendas/cover letters re task force meetings, summarizing reading materials; related reports
- Reading. AFT Task Force on Reading 1997-1998 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  "Every Child Reading: An Action Plan of the Learning First Alliance," June 1998; correspondence re International Reading Association's criticism of AFT position
- Reading. AFT Task Force on Reading 4/6/98, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  National Research Council pre-publication copy, "Preventing Reading Difficulties in Young Children," 1998; working draft of "Every Child Reading"; letter to the New York Times, criticizing coverage, from Judith Birsh, Columbia University Teachers College; related materials
- Reading. AFT Task Force on Reading. Notes 1997-1998 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  Analyses of California and Texas reading programs; statement of G. Reid Lyons, National Institutes of Health, before the House Committee on Education and the Workforce, July 10, 1997; handwritten notes
- Reading Conference Planning Meeting 3/25 /98, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  Tentative outline of policy document; handwritten notes; memo
- Reading. Essential Elements of Reading (folder 1 of 2) 1998 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  State Education Department (SED) Early Literacy Profile (assessment instrument), n.d., c.1998; SED Essentials Elements of Reading draft and final version, 1999; correspondence and reaction forms re plans
- Reading. Essential Elements of Reading (folder 2 of 2) 1999 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  Reading for Life 1997
- Reading for Life 1997 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  Resolution (Special Order of Business #1) adopted at NYSUT Representative Assembly, May 1-2, 1997, endorsing early reading plan, including guaranteed access to pre-K for all four-year-olds
- Reading Initiatives 1998 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  Summary of the Reading Excellence Act, prepared by AFT Department of Legislation, with cover letter, December 2, 1998; comments and excerpts from Learning to Read and Write: Developmentally Appropriate Practices for Young Children: A joint position statement of the International Reading Association and the National Association for the Education of Young Children, adopted 1998; comments by the Business Council of New York State, Inc., re Essential Elements of Reading document, November 12, 1998; correspondence re substantive debate on teaching methods to improve reading competency
- Reading Initiative 5/26/98, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  List of members of State Education Department Reading Initiative Committee; preliminary draft, "New York State Reading Initiative Policy Statement"; final report, "New York State Reading Symposium," February 11, 1998
- Reading Instruction 1997 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  Resource document, "Teacher Tasks, Knowledge, and Abilities (TKAs) Important for the Combined Delivery of a Balanced, Comprehensive Reading Curriculum to All Speakers, Including English Language Learners, Speakers of Non-Mainstream English, and Students with Special Needs, And Important for Newly Credentialed Teachers," based on a job analysis of the teaching of reading in California classrooms (K-8) by Educational Testing Service, adopted by the California Commission on Teacher Credentialing, July 1997; Public Policy Institute publication, "Separate and Unequal: The Reading Gap in New York's Elementary Schools," March 1998, with critiques, cover letter from Business Council; materials from Texas Reading Initiative; "Preventing Reading Difficulties in Young Children," Report of the Committee on the Prevention of Reading Difficulties in Young Children, created by the National Academy of Sciences for the U.S. Departments of Education and Health and Human Services, 1998; March 25, 1998; related articles and materials
- Reading. Elementary Literacy Profile September 25, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  NYSUT memo re details of use of profile to track student progress in reading and writing
- Redesigning Low-Performing Schools. See: Low-Performing Schools
- Board of Regents 1990-2000 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  Letter from NYS Senate Deputy Majority Whip James Lack (R) to Robert M. Johnson, expressing vehement disapproval of Johnson's decision to seek another five-year term as Regent, February 10, 2000; letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to members of district re motion that NYSUT work against re-election of Regent, March 21, 2000; revised NYSUT policy on selection procedure for Regents, June 15, 1990; correspondence and related materials re Emergency Campaign Against Vouchers, 1999; Response of NYSUT and NEA/NY to the Selected Positions of the Regents Task Force on Teaching (report dated September 17, 1997); correspondence with individual Regents re standards-based reform, other issues; press release re election of Carl Hayden and two other Regents, March 6, 1990
- Board of Regents. Membership 1978-1990 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  Biographical descriptions of Regents, 1979; map of Judicial Districts in NYS; list of Regents; newspaper clippings
- Board of Regents. Chancellor Hayden 11/6/98, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  Correspondence with Hayden re Reading for Life plan; newspaper article written by Hayden's son in response to criticism by Gannett News Service columnist Billy House, n.d.; biographical sketch of Hayden; meeting materials
- Regents Action Plan (folder 1 of 2) 1984-1990 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  "NYS Board of Regents Proposed Action Plan to Improve Elementary and Secondary Education Results in New York," revised February 1984; summary of Action Plan, February 8, 1985; testimony of Antonia Cortese, First Vice President, NYSUT, to the NYS Assembly Standing Committee in [sic] Education at the Public Hearing on Review of the Regents Action Plan, January 10, 1990; summary of comments from phone survey of NYSUT local leaders regarding the Assembly Education Committee's review of the Regent's Action Plan; NYSUT discussion paper on Action Plan, January 1984, with cover letter from Cortese to Commissioner Ambach; summary of selected regional conference responses in Action Plan, January 18, 1984
- Regents Action Plan (folder 2 of 2) 1984-1988 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  April 1984 version of Action Plan; NYSUT policy on Action Plan, approved by Board of Directors March 3, 1984; State Education Department highlights of the Second Annual Report on the Evaluation of the Implementation of the Regents Action Plan, February 25, 1988; handwritten notes, 1985
- Regents Candidates 2002 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  Sample interview questions; interview schedule with handwritten notes; resumes, correspondence, or interview transcripts with applicants Linda Beimer, Milton Cofield, Roy Dexheimer, Estella Norwood Evans, Danielle Kane, Judith O. Rubin, Anndrea Starzak; text of opening statement of Reinhold (Ray) W. Samson
- Regents Candidates 2001 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  Letter recommending candidate; resumes and application letters; interview transcripts and summary
- Regents Candidates: Joseph Bowman 2001 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  Resume
- Regents Candidates: Karen Schimke 2001 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  Newsletter, Early Ed Reports, featuring Schimke on cover, February 2001
- Regents Candidates: Carolyn Williams 2001 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  Resume; brochure
- Regents Interviews 2000 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  List of questions for candidates; resumes; interview summaries
- Regents Candidates: Anthony Shorris 2000 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  Cover note from Cortese: "I thought maybe you'd like to see the questions they might ask"; resume
- Regents Candidates: Harriet Cornell 2000 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  Letter of application
- Regents Candidates: Richard Kohlhausen 2000 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  Letter of application and three thank-you notes to Cortese
- Regents Candidates: Evelyn Stock 2000 (Box 22, Folder 19)
- Regents Competency Tests 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  NYSUT Special Order of Business #2, Response to the Commissioner's Proposal to Phase Out Regents Competency Tests; testimony of Cortese to the Regents and State Education Department at their 1997 Legislative Conference, re replacement of competency tests with Regents exams, September 18, 1996; handwritten note from teacher at Copiague High School expressing concern over new math standards, and five-page response from Cortese re Regents exams
- Regents Diploma 1990-1993 (Box 22, Folder 21)
  NYSUT Policy Paper and Recommendations on the Decline in the Percentages of Regents Diplomas Awarded to High School Graduates, revised 6/7/90; version of 6/25, with cover letter from Cortese to Commissioner Sobol, July 20, 1990; reply from Sobol, noting follow-up actions by State Education Department, August 3, 1990; statistical charts re high school graduation rates by district, racial/ethnic group, or public/non-public school, 1987-1993
- Regents Examinations. Representative Assembly Special Order of Business (Resolution) 1995 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  Resolution supporting increasing essay question component of Regents examination and related issues, with handwritten edits, 1995
- Regents Exams 1994-1997 (Box 22, Folder 23)
  Regents high school exams in physics, chemistry, biology, and earth science, 1994; NYSUT memo re translation of exams, with attached newspaper clippings, May 20, 1997; letter from Cortese to Commissioner Mills, objecting to moral relativism of 1996 English exam, July 12, 1996
- Regents Exams 2003 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  Agenda for meeting of NYSUT and NYSCOSS re Math A and Physics Regents Exams, June 25, 2003; confidential memo re NYSCOSS analysis of Physics and Math A Regents exams, June 24, 2003; talking points; State Education Department press release, "Commissioner Mills Makes Announcement on June Math A Regents Exam," June 24, 2003
- Regents Exams. Math A 2003 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  State Education Department independent panel report on Math A, October 1, 2003; statistical data; NYSUT press releases responding to Regents action; correspondence
- Regents Exams. Physics 2003-2004 (Box 22, Folder 26)
  Press release, "State Education Department Issues New Scores for June 2002-June 2003 Regents Physics Exams," January 9, 2004; talking points; NYSUT phone survey of teachers, September 2003; correspondence
- Regents Exams. Social Studies 1991-1993 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  Regents high school exams in U.S. history and government, 1991, and global studies, 1993; letter to Cortese from State Education Department lead specialist in social studies, noting essay questions requiring analysis rather than rote recall, September 21, 1993
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. See: Teaching
- Restructuring (folder 1 of 2) 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 28)